Farewell, Earth
The ship that is departing is
The Space Battleship
Yamato
It departs now to Iscandar
At the end of the cosmos
Bearing its fate
"We will come back, no matter what it takes"
Answer with a smile to the waving people
Going far from the Galaxy towards Iscandar
A faint gleam of hope
The Space Battleship Yamato
Last Episode
Memories of the Blue Planet
The ship sustained only minimal damage in the last fight.
It won't affect our return. There were seventeen dead.
Thirty-four wounded.
Damn it!
Operations Officer Mori was also shot, and is in a coma.
Any chance she'll recover?
Unfortunately,
a miracle would have to occur.
Miracles don't just happen.
You need to make them happen.
We have a channel open to Earth!
This is Todo, at Yamato Plan HQ.
Yamato, do you read me?
This is the Yamato. We have received the Cosmo Reverse System from Iscandar.
We're now returning to Earth.
I see. Then Iscandar was real!
You did it... You really did it!
We've waited this past year, gritting our teeth,
resting all our hopes on the Yamato's return.
Where is the Captain? Where is Okita?
His Planet Bomb Syndrome has returned, and he isn't in good shape.
Very well... Sanada, is Yuki all right?
Operations Officer Mori was wounded in combat. She's presently...
What's wrong, Yamato? Do you read me? Yamato!
The hyperspace relays are still unstable.
We're still working on them. Give me some time.
But we're back!
Yeah, we're back.
Hey... Just because we're near the
Solar System, don't lower your guard.
But now we know our families back on Earth are safe.
Did you hear that rumor about the ghost?
I heard it's wearing a Defense Force uniform now.
What I saw turned out to be Yurisha.
Too bad... I heard it's a guy this time.
A guy?
And what's more, it isn't a uniform from this ship!
Then, from another ship?
Why would a ghost from another ship be on the Yamato?
It's a mystery.
Yeah.
Come to think of it, Operations Officer Mori...
I know.
The XO suggested putting her in there.
If we can return to Earth, and get her to a real hospital...
No, even then, the probability of survival is under 0.1%...
But...
But it's still possible, right?
I don't think her body will last that long.
And so...
There's a way we can at least stabilize things.
We can use the capsule that kept
Yurisha alive while she was in a coma.
Captain...
Captain!
Are you all right? You were having a nightmare.
I was dreaming... About Mamoru Kodai.
Come to think of it, he was with us on the Kirishima.
You were the captain, and I ran the engines.
And he was a new Weapons Officer, yes?
You're talking about the Second Battle of Mars?
The one battle we won.
That success allowed us to push back the Garmillas invasion.
But much was lost there, as well.
Tokugawa...
Yes?
Don't you think this is a good ship?
It is.
I'm proud of this ship.
The flames of my life will not endure much longer.
But this ship will live on. I want to pass this soul to the younger generation.
Why so gloomy all of a sudden?
I won't die yet. Not until I've seen Earth with my own eyes.
I'll get going, then.
Yamazaki is talented, but I still haven't taught him all we must impart.
By the way, wasn't Mamoru Kodai meant to be on the Yamato?
His younger brother is doing his job just fine.
Nanbu. Nanbu.
What's wrong with Aihara?
That last communication with Earth...
Yes?
It's a hard truth to accept.
My father's dead... And my aging mother is alone at home.
They say that Earth's a mess!
At this rate, my mother won't last much longer, either...
It's true that Earth is nearly dead.
But crying won't save it.
The Yamato will make it! We'll make it in time!
We'll ensure it does!
He's kind of acting like the Captain.
Leave it to me! I've got the helm!
I'll get us to Earth ahead of schedule.
Who's got the helm?
Time for shift change.
I've been waiting for you!
Where's the XO?
He went to the Wave Motion Gun Control Room, to adjust the Cosmo Reverser.
I see.
Shima...
Kodai?
This one's for you.
Look at this.
Invitation to Kato and Harada's Wedding Party
It finally happened, huh?
It wasn't easy persuading Kato. He's so old fashioned.
Anyway, it's nice to have something cheery going on.
Is this really okay?
It didn't look good on me?
No, I mean... Us being the only ones that have something like this.
You mean Kodai?
He's forcing himself to act cheerful.
But in reality, he's falling apart.
It doesn't matter! Let's do this!
We must share our happiness with him!
Makoto...
I'm sure our child says the same thing.
You're right.
So decide which one is best.
Traditional Japanese kimonos, then.
No!
New life is born as the old passes away, huh?
Who are you talking about?
I don't know.
Anyway, since we left Iscandar,
you've been coming here frequently.
I suppose this place calms me.
I see... Then stay here forever.
Huh?
Stay here!
Yuki, Kato and I are getting married soon.
And then, get this...
Kodai says, "Have a party! You have to!"
That's what he told Kato. And Kato
was mortified, but ended up agreeing.
Guys are so cute, aren't they?
Yuki!
Finally... Just wait! I'll get the doctor!
Doctor! Get over here!
Where? To automatic navigation!
What do you think?
It's an interlocking recursive structure.
Like a brain's neural network.
The Cosmo Reverse System is like a living creature.
It's possible.
Then this wave motion pattern is the memory required to rebuild Earth?
The question is to whom that memory belongs.
You don't think it's the memories of the Yamato's crew?
I can't think of anything else.
But is that really it?
Could it be...
You?
Yes, this is the Wave Motion Control Room.
Don't yell at me like that!
Yes, the XO is here.
But what happened to Officer Mori, Doctor Sade?
Yes.
No...
Before she died, she miraculously opened her eyes.
The last thing she said was your name.
She said she wanted to see you again.
Me, too...
I wanted to see you again, too.
XO Sanada, I have a request.
Don't tell anyone about this.
At last, we're almost home.
I don't want them to hear any more sad news.
Congratulations on your marriage!
So it's our turn now, huh?
Congratulations.
And to you, Harada.
Thank you.
Kodai, do you remember when we were assigned to the Yamato?
Back then, I said this to you...
That if your orders caused one of my men to die needlessly, I'd never forgive you.
So...
You've done better than I could have hoped.
Better than anyone.
I guarantee that.
So Mori will be fine!
Sabu!
Wh-What?
Kato...
Make her happy.
Mamoru Kodai?
The system core is Kodai?
After following the chain of logic, that is my answer.
Doctor...
Have you heard the rumors about a ghost on the ship?
You might laugh at me for being unscientific,
but I saw it as well. It was Kodai.
"Any sufficiently advanced technology is
indistinguishable from magic," huh?
After he died on Iscandar,
Chuya Nakahara Poems
his memories were probably saved in some form.
We're almost close enough to see Earth up close!
Let's all go see it!
And his consciousness is the core to activate the Cosmo Reverse System.
Right now, Mamoru Kodai himself is the Cosmo Reverse System.
No, he is the Yamato itself.
Yuki...
Do you remember
the first time we met?
Back then, I was so angry about my brother...
It wasn't the best way to meet someone.
After that, we both came aboard the Yamato...
Our different ways of thinking meant we fought all the time.
But eventually,
you told me how you'd lost your memories.
And about how you kept trying to stay positive...
Without even knowing it,
I found myself drawn to you.
When you were kidnapped,
and when we met again...
I realized how I really felt.
I love you.
I love you more than anyone in the world.
Is there even any point
in a world without you?
Is there?
Susumu, this is all I can do for you.
I return your ship to you,
Captain Okita.
Activated
The system is starting up on its own!
No... Why?
I don't know!
Output is dropping fast!
Oh, no! At this rate...
Keep things steady! Don't shut down the Cosmo Reverser.
It's no good! It won't accept our commands.
No... Doctor!
Why?
Chuya Nakahara Poems
Why, Kodai?
Why did you start it now?
What is this?
Kodai?
Yuki!
Why am I...
I was shot, and then...
It was a dream.
A dream?
It was a dream. You were having a nightmare.
Kodai!
Inspect every part of the Cosmo Reverser! Prepare to reboot!
The activation pulse that was his mind...
It's almost entirely lost in the quantum sea.
It cannot be reactivated.
Then, even if the Yamato returns...
We won't be able to save Earth?
Kodai... No, Yamato!
Is this your will? Is this what you wanted?
Earth! We can see Earth!
Doctor Sado...
Would you leave me alone for a moment?
Thank you.
Earth, huh?
Everything brings back so many memories...
Rebooting
The Cosmo Reverse System has reactivated. What happened?
I don't know, but...
A miracle has occurred.
Mamoru!
Goodbye, Sanada.
Goodbye, Kaoru.
I guess stuff like this does happen.
Welcome back!
I'm back.
Welcome back.
Welcome home.
Mori!
We all welcome Officer Mori's return.
Thank you.
December 8th, 2199
Space Battleship Yamato returns to Earth.
NNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNNN
This star is the only one
If you look for something so beautiful
It is not something you can see
You will find it inside anyone
Love is the answer
Sorrow and strife
May cloud the blue sky
The overlapping warmth
Becomes a light to illuminate the world
A wish to the infinite universe
All is forgiven
And we all laugh together
Not a trick of the eye
But a dream from the bottom of my heart
No matter what tomorrow brings
Walk on
If you have nothing special
Only the strength to yearn for it
Bound to the limits of time
Create the trace of a miracle
A wish to the infinite universe
All is forgiven
And we all laugh together
Not a trick of the eye
A dream from the bottom of my heart
No matter what tomorrow brings
Walk on
Together with you
Forever